Alexander D. Bannon

alexbannon.com • alexbannon@gmail.com • github.com/alexbannon • 301-919-4523

Product-Focused Engineering Leader

I am a team-oriented, self-motivated, and product-focused engineering leader with over 10 years of experience creating software and over 7 years leading and managing cross-functional technical departments. My recent experience ranges across payments, content attribution and distribution at scale, and engineering compliance.

Kev Skills

Cross-functional leadership and collaboration, agile methodologies, stakeholder management, technical design, software development lifecycle, cross-team execution, Java, C#, Python, JavaScript, Ruby, Go, React, Node, .NET, PostgreSQL, BigQuery, BigTable, Mongo, Pub/Sub, Kafka, Lambda, GCS, AWS, Azure, Docker, K8s, Jenkins

Experience

Spotify

Technical Lead, Content Platform

February 2023 - Present

September 2021 - February 2023

- Engineering Manager II, Content Platform Head of the Content Understanding Vertical within content platform focused on the safe distribution and consumption of content to millions; composed of 5 teams in the ML, back-end, and data engineering space.
- Drove numerous compliance-related projects including the adoption of the Digital Services Act and Articles 17 and 19 of the GDPR focused on data privacy, data erasure, appeals, transparency, and data attribution.
- Increased monetized user-created podcasts by 20% through the use of in-house multimodal and 3rd party machine learning models including OpenAI, Hive AI, and Assembly AI.
- Scaled systems and teams by instituting agile processes, overhauling documentation and onboarding practices, setting a technical vision, and communicating and measuring key metrics.
- Align on and communicate vision, direction, and roadmaps with Group Product Managers and other vertical leads; Create the right incentives, measure progress, and eliminate roadblocks to enable effective execution.
- Inspire managers and staff engineers via mentorship, one-on-ones, goal-setting, feedback, and formal reviews.
- Oversee hiring of engineering managers, product managers, staff engineers, and senior engineers within two product areas, resulting in the growth of 25 new hires within 18 months.

Quadpay (Acquired By Zip Co)

Senior Engineering Manager, Payments

January 2020 - September 2021

- Managed the Payments Engineering Department which was responsible for all charges, refunds, and disbursements to merchants with roughly \$3bn in yearly transaction volume.
- Overhauled the hiring process with the help of co-members of the DEI committee, transitioning to pair programming away from whiteboarding algorithms, and standardizing questions to eliminate common biases.
- Instituted agile processes including sprint frameworks, fibonacci-style ticket sizing, refinement, estimation, commitment, and retros; measure and maintain velocity by identifying and getting ahead of blockers.
- Led on numerous projects including launching Quadpay in international markets, migrating from a monolithic architecture to microservices, compliance-driven changes to our fee structures, modernizing our accounting software and practices, implementing strong customer authentication, adapting to multiple payment processors and issuers, and scaling up our code and infrastructure to handle the 300%+ yoy growth.

Diatribe LLC - Founder, CEO

June 2019 - Present

- Founder of Diatribe, an ML and AI focused application that enables product and upper management to visualize their roadmap based on ever-changing user data, reports, feedback, and reviews.
- Python, Golang, GCS tech stack with multimodal model development to account for various user asset types.
- Manage contractors, lead on investor meetings, and handle all inbound requests from our largest stakeholder.

Alexander D. Bannon

alexbannon.com • alexbannon@gmail.com • github.com/alexbannon • 301-919-4523

Experience Continued

Kaplan, Inc - Head of Engineering at Metis

May 2018 - January 2020

- Built out and led the engineering department at the data-science division of Kaplan called Metis.
- Responsible for communicating velocity, vision, successes, and challenges directly to the President and C-Suite, coordinating top-down goals, KPIs, velocity, and deliverables utilizing agile methodologies.
- Managed a 20 person department through one-on-ones, mentorship, training, on-boarding, & direct feedback.
- Conduct product planning and prioritization meetings, scope projects before prioritization, design solutions to
 problems, head kickoff meetings, and communicate progress and data-driven results back to key stakeholders.

Blackbook - Co-Founder, CTO

September 2016 – December 2018

- Co-Founded, built, and expanded a FinTech mobile ordering and payment app that boosted revenue by as much as \$75K per year at various clubs and restaurants in the Washington, DC area.
- Managed the engineering and product teams, working alongside the CEO as we built up the company.
- Led on investment and client meetings to secure new funding and contracts.
- Built a Point of Sale integration into restaurant systems in DC utilizing Ionic/Cordova, Angular 2, Node, Koa, JavaScript, MongoDB, and Mongoose.

Mobile Posse (Acquired By Digital Turbine)

Senior Full Stack Software Engineer

Full Stack Software Engineer

December 2016 - June 2017

October 2015 – December 2016

- Created and maintained various user-facing applications built in Node, Express, Postgres, and Angular as well
 as sites built with Node, Express, Handlebars, and DynamoDB.
- Formalized the onboarding process for new hires. Established and maintained best coding/testing practices.
- Updated gulp build processes and node versions and implemented new tools for analytics tracking.
- Oversaw the migration of ad providers from AdSense to header bidding and DFP.

Consultant - Software Engineer

August 2011 – October 2015

- Key clients included National Education Association, NARAL, Center for Global Policy Solutions, DNC
- Built public-facing and internal web apps for policy-focused clients primarily utilizing JavaScript frameworks and relational databases (MySQL, PostgreSQL), with a focus on data security and data management.
- Applications varied in complexity from maintaining simple brochure sites to automatically ingesting news and votes on legislation to build up databases for opposition research.

Education, Courses, and Certifications

Hunter College

Boston University

Computer Science, Non-Degree

B.A. Philosophy, Minor in Political Science B.S. Film and Television

- Introduction to Computer Science Harvard/edX Online 2014
- Algorithms Part 1 Princeton/Coursera Online 2017
- Algorithms Part 2 Princeton/Coursera Online 2017
- Multivariate Calculus 2 Hunter College In Person 2019
- Discrete Structures Hunter College In Person 2019
- Computer Theory I Hunter College Hybrid Online/In-Person 2020
- OWASP Top 10 PCI Compliance Certification Online 2020
- Automata Theory Stanford Online 2021
- Self Supervised Machine Learning Greenhouse Online 2022
- Google Cloud Professional Certification Online 2023